<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GitHub | Computational Psychology</title>
    <link>http://haines-lab.com/category/github/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://haines-lab.com/category/github/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>GitHub</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Nathaniel Haines, PhD</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://haines-lab.com/media/icon_hu88408da40bfce0858e3c9c463b923e62_76530_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>GitHub</title>
      <link>http://haines-lab.com/category/github/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automating Computational Reproducibility in R using renv, Docker, and GitHub Actions</title>
      <link>http://haines-lab.com/post/2022-01-23-automating-computational-reproducibility-with-r-using-renv-docker-and-github-actions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://haines-lab.com/post/2022-01-23-automating-computational-reproducibility-with-r-using-renv-docker-and-github-actions/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;http://haines-lab.com/post/2022-01-23-automating-computational-reproducibility-with-r-using-renv-docker-and-github-actions/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;the-problem&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wanted to run someone else’s R code (or your own—from a distant past), but upon downloading it, you realized that it relied on versions of either R or R libraries that are dramatically different from those on your own computer? This situation can easily spiral into &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_hell&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;dependency hell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a place that every researcher or data scientist will (always unintentionally) find themselves when trying to get random code from bygone days to run locally. Oftentimes, it may seem impossible to resolve The Problem, and giving up may seem like the only logical thing to do…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/dependencies.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Caption: Occasionally, dependency hell peak’s its head into the real world too&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-naive-attempt-to-resolve-the-problem&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Naive Attempt to Resolve The Problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are like me, the first thing you might do when finding yourself in dependency hell is to try installing different versions of the R libraries that R is complaining about. If that doesn’t work, you may even get desperate enough to try installing a different version of R in hopes that The Problem will magically disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, the naive attempt &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; succeed. But alas, it will often fail, and even when it does succeed—that different version of R (or R libraries) you installed could lead to problems in other ongoing projects. You know, the projects that you briefly forgot about while trying to resolve The Problem for the current project on the to-do list. In this case, dependency hell has evolved into &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whac-A-Mole#Colloquial_usage&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;computational whac-a-mole&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—a rage-inducing game that your therapist told you to stop playing many sessions ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-slightly-better-attempt-but-it-requires-foresight&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A Slightly Better Attempt, But It Requires Foresight&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
